<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament containing certaine instructions to be issued by the Committee for the Admiralty and Cinque-Ports, to such fit persons as shall desire to set forth ships as private men of warre. Die Iovis, 29 Ianuarii 1645. Ordered by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, that this ordinance be forthwith printed and published. Joh. Brown Cler. Parliamentorum. H. Elsynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1832</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E330_27</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200730</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861395</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861395</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159634</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159634)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 54:E330[27])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament containing certaine instructions to be issued by the Committee for the Admiralty and Cinque-Ports, to such fit persons as shall desire to set forth ships as private men of warre. Die Iovis, 29 Ianuarii 1645. Ordered by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, that this ordinance be forthwith printed and published. Joh. Brown Cler. Parliamentorum. H. Elsynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Wright at the Kings Head in the old Bayley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645. [i.e. 1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing has publication year 1645; Thomason catalogue lists under 1646.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 7th 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Privateering --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Naval operations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159634:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An ORDINANCE OF THE LORDS and COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT Containing certaine INSTRUCTIONS To be iſſued by the Committee for the Admiralty and Cinque-Ports, to ſuch fit Perſons as ſhall deſire to ſet forth Ships as private men of Warre.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Die Iovis</hi> 29 <hi>Ianuarii</hi> 1645.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That this Ordinance be forthwith printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Joh. Brown Cler. Parliamentorum.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Iohn Wright</hi> at the Kings Head in the old Bayley. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb facs="tcp:159634:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159634:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Die Iovis,</hi> 29. <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1645. An Ordinance of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Aſſembled in Parliament, concerning certaine Inſtructions to be iſſued by the Committee for the Admiralty and Cinque-ports, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the Committee of Lords and Commons for the Admiralty and Cinque Ports, are by an Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized and enabled to doe and execute all ſuch things as appertaine to the Office of Lord High Admirall of England. And whereas it is Ordained by another Ordinance of Parliament, dated 30 <hi>November</hi> 1643. That it ſhall and may be lawfull for any his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties good Subjects, that ſhall be approved and thereunto apointed by the Lord High Admirall of England, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by both Houſes for the time being, in warlike manner to Equipp, arme, furniſh, Man, and ſet out to Sea, ſuch and ſo many Ships as they ſhall thinke fitting, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159634:3"/>with the ſame to ſeize, ſurprize, and take all and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Ships, and Veſſels, which they ſhall meet withall, in or outwards bound from any Port, or place within any his Majeſties Dominions, being in Hoſtility againſt the Parliament, or comming from, or returning to any ſuch Port or place; or that ſhall be found to have Traded with the Inhabitants of any ſuch Port or place, ſince their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from the King and Parliament; and alſo to ſeaze, ſurprize and take all, and all manner of Pyrats, and Sea-Rovers of what Nation ſoever, and their Ships and Goods whatſoever; And that the Ships to be ſo employed ſhall have liberty to ſeeke, and take their purchaſe where, and how they pleaſe, according to ſuch inſtructions as ſhal from time to time be given them by the Lord High Admirall of England, or the Commiſſioners of the Admiralty appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by both Houſes for the time being. And whereas this Committee hath been Petitioned, by <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Owners of the Ship the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> for our approving of them, to employ the ſhid Ship under Command of Captaine <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in execution of the powers granted by the ſaid Ordinance; We do hereby ſignifie and declare, That we have approved and appointed, and do hereby approve, and appoint the ſaid Petitioners in warlike manner to Equipp, furniſh, and arme the ſaid Ship, the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and to place in her a competent number of Souldiers, Marriners, and Gunners, with neceſſary Armes and Proviſions, and the ſame ſo Manned, Equipped, Armed, and provided to ſet forth to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159634:3"/>Sea, under command of the ſaid Captaine <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> And the ſaid Captaine <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> to employ the ſaid Ship, for doing and performing the Services hereafter mentioned; That is to ſay, For the ſeazing, taking, and ſurprizing of all Ships, and Veſſels belonging to any of his Majeſties Subjects, which the ſaid Ship ſhall meete withall, in or outwards bound from any Port or place, within any of his Majeſties Dominions being in Hoſtility againſt the Parliament, together with all the Ordnance, Ammunition, Victuals, Goods, Commanders and Souldiers therein; as alſo for the ſeazing, ſurprizing, and taking of all and all manner of Ships, and Veſſels whatſoever, with the Ordnance, Ammunition, Victuals, and Goods therein belonging to any Rebell or Rebels in Ireland; and alſo the Ships and Goods of any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever, Forraigner or other, which ſhall be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to or comming from any Port or place in Ireland in Hoſtility againſt the Parliament; as alſo for the ſeazing, ſurprizing, and taking of all and all manner of Ships, and Veſſels belonging to any Forraigner or forraigne Nation, going to any Port or place in Hoſtility againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with Armes, Ammunition, or other <hi>Contrabando</hi> Goods for ſupply of the Forces raiſed againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and adjudging and condemning the ſame, together with the Goods themſelves, and all ſuch other Goods as belong to the Maſters, or Laders of ſuch <hi>Contrabando</hi> Goods as alſo for the ſeazing, ſurprizing, and taking of all Pyrats, and Sea-Rovers of what Nation ſoever, and their Ships and Goods whatſoever, according to the authority, meaning, and true intent of the ſaid Ordinance of the 30. of <hi>November,</hi> 1643. Provided that before the going forth of the ſaid Ship, the ſaid Captain <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> together with the Maſter, and principall Officers thereof, or ſuch
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159634:4"/>other ſufficient perſons in their behalfe, as ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of by the Judge of the Admiralty for the time being, doe and ſhall enter into Bond of two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds in the Admiralty Court, with condition, That neither the ſaid Commander of the ſaid Ship, nor the Maſter or Company, or any of them, ſhall (under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of the ſaid Ordinance, or of theſe Inſtructions) ſpoile or damage any of the Kings Subjects, nor any of the friends or Allies of this Kingdome, other then ſuch as are intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſaid Ordinance and theſe Inſtructions; As alſo, that for juſtification of the prize or prizes that the ſaid Commander ſhall take, he ſhall bring into the Regiſtry of the High Court of Admiralty, all ſuch Cocquets, Bills of Lading, and other Documents and Writings, as he or any of his Company ſhall take or find in any ſuch Ship or Veſſel, and ſhall bring in with every ſuch Ship or Veſſell, two or three of the principall Officers thereof taken in the ſame, to be examined by the Judge of the Admiralty, or ſuch as he ſhall appoint, concerning the property of the ſaid Ship, Veſſel or goods therein, and to ſuch other queſtions and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogatories, as he ſhall thinke fit to adminiſter in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe: And alſo that neither he, they, nor any of them, ſhall breake Bulke, ſpoile, waſt, or diminiſh any of the ſaid Ships, or Goods, untill they ſhall be adjudged in the High Court of Admiralty to have been lawfully taken, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the true intent and meaning of the ſaid Ordinance, and theſe Inſtructions; and a true and juſt Inventory and appraiſement be taken and made of the ſame: And the Judge of the Admiralty is hereby prayed and required to take Bond accordingly, and to certifie the ſame under the Seal of the Admiralty Court, without which no benefit is to accrue to the ſaid Commander, Officers, Marriners, or any
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159634:4"/>others intereſſed in the ſaid Ship, by any thing done in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance thereof; And the ſaid Captaine <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ſhall truly pay and deliver to ſuch Collectors or Receivers as both Houſes of Parliament, the Committee of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty, or the Lord High Admirall for the time being, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by both Houſes of Parliament, have or ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the full Tenthes of every ſuch prize, as ſhall be taken by vertue of the ſaid Ordinance, or theſe Inſtructions.</p>
            <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, That the Committee for the Admiralty, do give Inſtructions to ſuch fit perſons as ſhall deſire to ſet forth Ships as private men of War, according to the tenor aforeſaid, notwithſtanding any former Order or Ordinance to the contrary.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Io. Browne Cleric. Parliamentorum.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
